<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright 2006 Inqwell Ltd.
-->
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V2.0//EN" "http://forrest.apache.org/dtd/document-v20.dtd">
<document>
  <header>
    <title>My Orders</title>
  </header>
  <body>
    <section id="intro">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>
        The My Orders window is used to browse previously submitted orders by
        specifying the desired date range. It illustrates the following Inq features:
      </p>
      <dl>
        <dt><strong>The Window Menu Bar</strong></dt>
        <dd>
          Inq's support for setting up a window's menu bar and building menus.
        </dd>
        <dt><strong>Keys As Filters</strong></dt>
        <dd>
          The <code>Order</code> typedef defines a key called <code>Filter</code>.
          We look at how this key is applied to SQL and its use of Inq's caching
          system. 
        </dd>
        <dt><strong>Listening For Created Orders In The Server</strong></dt>
        <dd>
          The server code for My Orders listens for events raised when new orders
          are created and uses them to maintain the summary table of orders.  
        </dd>
        <dt><strong>Listening For Node Events In The Client</strong></dt>
        <dd>
          Using event listeners in the client is just as valid as the
          server. My Orders uses a listener to keep the items totals row
          up to date when an order is selected in the summary table. 
        </dd>
        <dt><strong>Writing Reports</strong></dt>
        <dd>
          My Orders implements pdf reports by using Inq's ability
          to transform node structures into XML and deploys Inq's <em>file
          transfer</em> package to return the generated files to the client.
        </dd>
        <dt><strong>Table GUI Events</strong></dt>
        <dd>
          Any items in an order that are not yet shipped by
          the <a href="orderprocessor.html#intro">Order Processor</a>
          can be cancelled by clicking on the icon in the status column of
          the <em>Items</em> table. Code for this table is shared
          with the New Order function - soliciting table events and the information
          Inq provides in them is
          described <a href="neworder.html#tableevents">there</a>.
        </dd>
      </dl>
      <p>
      </p>
<!--
        In this section we
        cover: 
      <ul>
        <li>Setting up a menu bar</li>
        <li>Using filters</li>
        <li>Listening for new orders</li>
        <li>Writing Reports</li>
      </ul>
-->
      <p>
        Here is what the My Orders window looks like:
      </p>
      <figure src="images/psmyorders.png" alt="myorders"/>
    </section>
    <section id="menu">
      <title>The Menu Bar</title>
      <p>  
        To add a menu bar to a window, set its <code>menuBar</code> property:
      </p>
      <source>
// Menu Bar
myOrders.properties.menuBar = call createMenu(context=myOrders, i18n);
</source>
      <p>
        The menu bar and contents are created by the <code>createMenu()</code>
        function. My Orders just has a <em>File</em> menu:
      </p>
      <source>
gMenuBar menuBar;

gMenu fileMenu;
fileMenu.properties.text={i18n}.ps.button.FILE;
</source>
      <p>
        Next, the menu items are created and initialised, as in this
        example (the others have been omitted for brevity):
      </p>
      <source>
// Generate a printable of the filtered orders
gMenuButton filePrintSummary;
filePrintSummary.properties.text={i18n}.ps.button.PRINT_SUMMARY;
filePrintSummary.properties.icon = $catalog.icons.pdf16;
gEvent(filePrintSummary, call printSummary());
</source>
      <p>
        The following statement lays out the menu and its menu items:
      </p>
      <source>
// Layout the menu
layout(., context, menuBar,
       "fileMenu
        {
          fileNew
          Separator
          filePrintSummary
          filePrintOrder
          Separator
          fileClose
        }
        ");
</source>
      <note>
        In this example of <code>layout()</code> there are four arguments, because
        the graphical root is not the same as
        the Inq node.
      </note>
      <p>
        The graphical root is <code>menuBar</code> while the Inq node where the
        components are all placed is <code>context</code> (the <code>myOrders</code>
        window). The <code>menuBar</code> component accepts menus as its immediate
        children and the open-brace <code>{</code> causes <code>layout</code> to
        descend in the graphical hierarchy. This menu includes separators, created
        during the layout with the <code>Separator</code> keyword. Here is the result:
      </p>
      <figure src="images/myordersmenu.png" alt="myordersmenu"/>
      <p>
        Menus can be nested in the layout string by using successive matched braces
        to define the menu items at the next level. 
      </p>
    </section>
    <section id="filter">
      <title>Using a Filter</title>
      <p>
        The <code>Order</code> typedef defines a key called <code>Filter</code>. The
        purpose of this key is to return a lesser or greater number of instances
        according to tighter or looser input values. To <em>wild-card</em> an input
        value the key implementation uses Inq's <code>null</code> value. Furthermore
        this key uses two input values (of type <code>date</code> in this example)
        to specify a range.
      </p>
      <section id="keydefs">
        <title>Key Definition</title>
        <p>
          Here is the implementation of the key from <code>Order.inq</code>:
        </p>
        <source>
key Filter cached=true
(
  // This example defines fields in the key that are not part of the
  // typedef. FromDate and ToDate exist in the key only.
  fields(Account,
         Status,
         Date.Date FromDate,
         Date.Date ToDate)

  eligible
  (
    // This key is cached while at the same time containing an inequality.
    // Once an order is placed the OrderDate field never changes but we
    // could just as well create new Orders whose OrderDate would satisfy
    // a cached key's date range. To maintain a correct cache we define an
    // eligibility expression. It must match the sql where clause.
    $this.instance.Account   == $this.key.Account &amp;&amp;
    ($this.instance.Status   == $this.key.Status || isnull($this.key.Status)) &amp;&amp;
    ($this.instance.OrderDate &gt;= $this.key.FromDate || isnull($this.key.FromDate)) &amp;&amp;
    ($this.instance.OrderDate &lt;= $this.key.ToDate || isnull($this.key.ToDate))
  )

  // When defining the database binding information for this key
  // we include a "read-order" element. This is because the key
  // fields are used more than once in the where clause, that is
  // we cannot rely on the key field declaration order to initialise
  // the prepared statement parameters.
  auxcfg( map(
  "prepared", true,
  "read-sql",
    "
      {select-stmt}
      where O.userid = ?
      and (O.Status = ? OR ? IS NULL)
      and (O.orderdate &gt;= ? OR ? IS NULL)
      and (O.orderdate &lt;= ? OR ? IS NULL)
    ",
  "read-order",
    array a = (
                "Account",
                "Status",       "Status",
                "FromDate",     "FromDate",
                "ToDate",       "ToDate"
              )

  ))
)
</source>
        <p>
          This key defines four fields. We can see in its SQL <code>where</code>
          clause and associated configuration how these are used, including an array
          to guide the parameter substitution.
        </p>
        <p>
          Keys are discussed in <a href="../../primer/keys.html">More About I/O Keys</a>.
          The <code>eligible()</code> expression mirrors the <code>where</code> clause, so
          when new orders are created or the <code>Status</code> field of existing ones
          changes Inq maintains its cache accordingly.
        </p>
      </section>
      <section id="clientfilter">
        <title>The Client</title>
        <p>
          The filter components are created and laid out as a unit
          in <code>gui/myOrders.inq:createFilterBar()</code>.
        </p>
        <figure src="images/myordersfilter.png" alt="myordersfilter"/>
        <p>
          The data these
          components are bound to is an instance of the <code>Order.Filter</code>
          key:
        </p>
        <source>
// Create the data the filter bar components will operate on.
// This is an instance of Order.Filter
any context.vars.filter = new(Order.Filter);
</source>
        <p>
          The components themselves are created much like other the other
          examples already discussed however there are a few interesting
          features used by the filter.
        </p>
        <section id="filtercheck">
          <title>Check Box Values</title>
          <p>
            We saw when looking at
            the <a href="neworder.html#popupmenus">popup menu</a> used in the Item
            Chooser how check components support different values for their
            checked and unchecked state. To implement the desired functionality
            of the filter's check box we can set up these values as follows: 
          </p>
          <source>
gCheck cStatus;
cStatus.properties.checkedValue = enum(OStatus, O);
cStatus.properties.uncheckedValue = null;
cStatus.properties.renderInfo = renderinfo($this.vars.filter.Status, label={i18n}.ps.button.OPEN_ONLY);
</source>
          <p>
            With these properties in effect, toggling the check box sets
            the <code>Status</code> field of the filter to the <code>OPEN</code>
            order status or <code>null</code>, as we require. 
          </p>
        </section>
        <section id="filterdate">
          <title>The Date Choosers</title>
          <p>
            Inq
            incorporates <a class="fork" href="ext:jcalendar">Kai Toedter's JCalendar</a>
            as its <em>date chooser</em> component. For the filter we use two
            date choosers like this:
          </p>
          <source>
// Two date choosers for the date range
gDateChooser dcFromDate;
gDateChooser dcToDate;
dcFromDate.properties.renderInfo = renderinfo($this.vars.filter.FromDate,
                                              typedef=Order.OrderDate,
                                              format="dd MMM yyyy",
                                              width=8,
                                              label={i18n}.ps.general.FROM_DATE);
dcToDate.properties.renderInfo   = renderinfo($this.vars.filter.ToDate,
                                              typedef=Order.OrderDate,
                                              format="dd MMM yyyy",
                                              width=8,
                                              label={i18n}.ps.general.TO_DATE);

// The from date cannot be null (which referring to Order.Filter
// means the field is ignored) so we are preventing the user from going
// back to the beginning of time.
dcFromDate.properties.nullText   = null;
</source>
          <p>
            By default a date chooser allows the null value. This can be established
            by the user hitting <code>ctrl-n</code> in the focused date chooser.
            If the component is rendering the null date it displays the default
            text <code>&lt;none&gt;</code>. The <code>nullText</code> property
            allows this text to be changed or the null value to be prevented by
            setting <code>nullText</code> to null.
          </p>
        </section>
        <section id="filterreset">
          <title>Resetting The Filter</title>
          <p>
            Included in the filter components is a <em>reset</em> button. This
            is scripted to call the function <code>resetFilter()</code> function,
            which demonstrates date arithmetic:
          </p>
          <source>
local function resetFilter(any filter)
{
  // Default the from date to today minus one month. Default
  // the end date to open
  filter.FromDate = dateadd(MONTH, -1, getdate());
  filter.ToDate   = null;
}
</source>
          <p>
            The <code>createFilterBar()</code> function returns the component
            it laid out its components in, so that client script can place it
            in the wider GUI under construction.
          </p>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section id="serverfilter">
        <title>The Server</title>
        <p>
          The filter is used in two ways by server-side script, found
          in <code>psOrders.inq</code>.
        </p>
        <section id="serverapply">
          <title>Applying The Filter</title>
          <p>
            The client invokes the <code>filterOrders</code> service, supplying the
            filter as set by the GUI and the path where the server should
            place the resulting node-set.
          </p>
          <figure src="images/filterorders.png" alt="filterorders"/>
          <p>
            This service makes no formal response. Instead it uses event
            propagation from server to client as the means to return the
            data. Inq's automatic handling of such events received at the
            client is to place the node set at the same path, in turn
            generating an event in the client which is dispatched to
            the <em>Orders</em> table. 
          </p>
<!--
          <source>
service filterOrders(any filter, any at)
{
  any list = call filterOrders(filter);
  
  // Place the list in the context, raising an event as we do so.
  // Any events now occurring within the structure will be propagated
  // to the client.
  add(list, at);
</source>
-->
        </section>
        <section id="serverlisten">
          <title>Listening For New Orders</title>
          <p>
            When discussing the New Order function we showed how
            the <a href="neworder.html#crevent">event</a>
            raised by Inq on successful instance creation can
            carry some user-supplied data. This data acts as additional
            discrimination, allowing consumers to filter events of
            interest to them.
          </p>
          <p>
            In this example an instance of <code>Order.Filter</code> has been
            used for this data. Using a key instance is just a convenience - any
            kind of map, however created, can be used. When considering how
            parts of the system communicate via events, filtering them is
            part of the design. For a given event flow (in this
            case <code>Order</code> creation) all participants must
            agree on the form the create event data will take.  
          </p>
          <p>
            Our event flow arranges for new orders to appear on the My Orders
            screen, provided the order matches the event filtering currently
            in place. The following diagram depicts this flow: 
          </p>
          <figure src="images/listenorders.png" alt="listenorders"/>
          <p>
            Although this diagram shows two clients cooperating via their
            presence in the server, its equally valid (and more appropriate
            in petstore) that a <a href="../../primer/process.html">User Process</a>
            receives its own events. Inq makes no distinction in this regard.   
          </p>
          <p>
            The <code>filterOrders()</code> service arranges to
            receive <code>Order</code> creation events with the following
            statement: 
          </p>
          <source>
any $this.listeners.newOrder = listen (unlisten($catalog, $this.listeners.newOrder),
                                       func f = call newOrderCreated(listenInfo, Order = @eventData),
                                       event = (create),
                                       create  = call makeCreateListenData(filter),
                                       typedef = Order,
                                       listenInfo);
</source>
          <p>
            In fact, there are two complementary Inq functions being
            used - <code>listen()</code>
            and <code>unlisten()</code>. The arguments to <code>listen()</code>
            are as follows (the first three arguments are mandatory, the
            remainder optional):
          </p>
          <table>
            <caption>listen() example arguments [Full explanation of listen() is TODO]</caption>
            <tr>
              <th>Name</th>
              <th>Description</th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td/>
              <td>
                <p>
                  The node to listen to. When listening for <code>create</code>
                  events this is always <code>$catalog</code> because
                  all such events emanate from there.
                </p>
                <p>
                  Note that <code>unlisten</code> (explained below) returns its first
                  argument.
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td/>
              <td>
                <p>
                  The function to dispatch to. Does not have to be a <code>call</code>
                  statement, instead it can be any <em>closure</em> style
                  statement.
                </p>
                <p>
                  When the function executes the stack is initialised by Inq as
                  explained below.
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td><p><code>event = (...)</code></p></td>
              <td>
                <p>
                  A comma-separated list of event types. This example is only
                  interested in <code>create</code> events.
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td><p><code>create = &lt;expression&gt;</code></p></td>
              <td>
                <p>
                  The create listen data. This is the complement of the
                  value produced by <code>makeCreateRaiseData()</code>
                  discussed in <a href="neworder.html#crevent">New Order</a>.
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td><p><code>typedef = &lt;typedef-literal&gt;</code></p></td>
              <td>
                <p>
                  A literal type reference whose <code>create</code> events we
                  want to receive.
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td><p><code>listenInfo</code></p></td>
              <td>
                <p>
                  An example of a trailing argument whose value is placed on
                  the stack when an event is dispatched.
                </p>
              </td>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <p>
            The return value of <code>listen</code> is a token that represents
            the event binding. Script can retain this token for future use
            in removing the binding with <code>unlisten()</code>.
          </p>
          <note>
            Other than when replacing a listener with a new one, it is not
            necessary to tidy listeners up. If the User Process terminates Inq
            will remove defunct listeners automatically.
          </note>
          <p>
            The <code>unlisten()</code> function itself returns its first
            argument (the node from which the event binding is being removed)
            and tolerates that its second (the event binding) is unresolved, to
            support the <code>listen(unlisten(...))</code> construct. Each
            time <code>filterOrders()</code> is invoked any existing listener is
            discarded and a new one established with the prevailing filter data
            represented in the <code>create</code> argument, returned
            by the call to <code>makeCreateListenData(any filter)</code>:
          </p>
          <source>
local function makeCreateListenData(any filter)
{
  any createData.Account   = isnull(filter.Account, equals);
  any createData.Status    = isnull(filter.Status, equals);
  
  // Event filtering is only by equality. As we are dealing with a date range
  // we let all creations through and check in the dispatch function. This is
  // OK because in this case we are only listening to our own data.
  any createData.FromDate  = equals;
  any createData.ToDate    = equals;

  // returns
  createData;
}
</source>
          <p>
            We can see that this function creates its map "by implication"
            rather than using an instance of <code>Order.Filter</code>
            like <a href="neworder.html#crevent"><code>makeCreateRaiseData()</code></a> does.
            This is incidental. What is important is that the map content (which
            must use the same <em>key set</em> as the one used
            in <code>create()</code>) wild-cards any of its fields using
            the <code>equals</code> constant. This is a special value that always
            yields <code>true</code> when compared with anything.
          </p>
          <p>
            You may notice that the <code>FromDate</code> and <code>ToDate</code>
            are always set to <code>equals</code>. This is because at present,
            discrimination by event data only supports equality. Given that these
            parameters specify a range, there is currently no way to express
            this. Instead the dispatch function performs an additional check
            to see that the new Order's <code>Order.OrderDate</code> falls within the
            the current filter's range:
          </p>
          <source>
local function newOrderCreated(any Order, any listenInfo)
{

  if (call isNewInstanceInDateRange(listenInfo.filter, Order))
  {
    // Make a node set child for the new Order
    hmap m;
    any m.Order = Order;

    // Add it into the list, causing it to appear on the GUI screen.
    any pKey = getprimarykey(Order);
    add(m, path($this.{listenInfo.at}.{pKey}));
  }
}
</source>
          <p>
            What processing does the dispatch function perform? It needs to add
            the new order to the 
            current <a href="../../primer/structures.html#nodeset">node-set</a>
            structure in the server: 
          </p>
          <ul>
          <li>it creates the map <code>m</code> as a suitable node-set child;</li>
          <li>places the new Order beneath <code>m</code>
            as <code>m.Order</code>;</li>
          <li>acquires the unique key of the Order and uses
              it <a href="../../primer/structures.html#nsetnames">to
              add</a> <code>m</code> to the node-set.</li>
          </ul> 
          <p>
            The last step causes the new node-set child to be propagated
            to the client where, similarly when applying the filter, it is
            replicated at the same path, processed by Inq's MVC and dispatched
            to the table. 
          </p>
        </section>
        <section id="serverstruct">
          <title>Structuring The Code For Desktop and Web Clients</title>
          <p>
            Long before reaching this point you will have realised that
            the Inq implementation of petstore is not a web application
            as such. Of course, this refers only to the client, which has
            been implemented to demonstrate Inq's capabilities with respect
            to the desktop. 
          </p>
          <p>
            As well as this Inq supports the construction of web-based
            applications, allowing the server-side script to be reused but
            changing the client technology. What are the differences
            between the two architectures? 
          </p>
          <table>
            <caption>Comparison Of Desktop and Web-based Inq Applications</caption>
            <tr>
              <th>Desktop</th>
              <th>Web</th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Client has a permanent, bidirectional connection to the server</td>
              <td>Client makes a connection to the server for each request</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Server may invoke services in the client or send it events</td>
              <td>Server cannot initiate an exchange with the client</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Server maintains complex state on behalf of the client</td>
              <td>Server maintains minimal state for subsequent client connections</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Server knows when client disconnects</td>
              <td>Server times out client if it never connects again</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Client/Server custom protocol</td>
              <td>Client/Server standard protocol (including firewalling)</td>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <figure src="images/deskweb.png" alt="deskweb.png"/>
          <note>
            Explanation of how Inq generates JSON when working with web apps and
            integration with JavaScript is TODO.
          </note>
          <p>
            For filtering orders, the call structure for the desktop is as follows:
          </p>
          <source>
Client
 |
 |--service filterOrders()
     |
     |-------call filterOrders()
               |
 |&lt;--event-- add list to node space
             establish new order listener
        
</source>
          <p>
            Adding the current orders list to the node space and listening
            for new orders are things only relevant to the desktop client.
            In the web case, the return value of the service makes up the
            data returned to the browser client. The process of applying
            the filter is factored out into
            the <em>function</em> <code>filterOrders</code>, and a suitable
            entry point <code>webFilterOrders</code> is created for it. The
            call structure for the web app case looks like this:
          </p>
          <source>
Browser
 |
 |--service webFilterOrders()
     |
     |-------call filterOrders()
               |
 |&lt;--returns---| 
        
</source>
          <p>
            In the web app case there is no persistent state held in the
            server, other than the session's connection to the Inq server. 
          </p>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="clientlisten">
      <title>Listening For Events in the Client</title>
      <p>
        In the majority of cases, the listsners Inq sets up internally when
        binding views to models are sufficient to drive the GUI from the
        events occurring in the node space. Sometimes however, it is necessary
        to script explicit event handlers for node events.
      </p>
      <p>
        My Orders needs to update the total order value, displayed in
        the items table totals row, when a selection is made from the
        filtered orders list. The <code>listen()</code> function is
        equally supported in the client as it is in the server; the client
        sets up a listener with this statement: 
      </p>
      <source>
// listen to $this.itemTable.properties.modelRoot so that when
// the items list is replaced the order total is displayed
listen ($this,
        func f = 
        {
          call calcOrderTotal();
        },
        event  = (add, remove, replace),
        path   = $this.vars.items  // NB listen path must be literal at the moment
       );
</source>
      <p>
        This example listens to the context node, <code>$this</code>,
        and uses <code>listen()</code>'s optional <code>path</code>
        argument to discriminate for events originating
        at the root of the items data, <code>$this.vars.items</code>.
        If a node is added at that location, removed or replaced with
        a new one (seen as distinct from <code>add</code>) the listener
        will fire. The
        function <code>calcOrderTotal</code> (in <code>gui/newOrder.inq</code>)
        simply reevaluates the rendered data: 
      </p>
      <source>
function calcOrderTotal()
{
  $this.vars.orderTotal.row.OrderTotal.Price =
    $this.vars.items ? isnull(sum($this.vars.items, $loop.LineItem.Qty * $loop.LineItem.UnitPrice), 0)
                     : 0;
}
</source>
    </section>
    <section id="reports">
      <title>Creating Printable Reports</title>
      <p>
        My Orders includes two printable reports - one at a summary
        level for the filtered order set and one for a selected
        order and its items. Writing reports in Inq combines Inq's ability
        to transform a node structure into XML with an external
        PDF generator such
        as <a class="fork" href="ext:fop">Apache FOP</a>. This
        XML is processed against an XSLT style sheet to
        create the report as <code>&lt;fo:</code>... Formatting Objects XML.
      </p>
      <figure src="../../primer/images/report.png" alt="fopreport"/>
      <p>
        Report generation is performed by the server and petstore
        deploys the Inq bundled package <em>filexfer</em> to
        return the PDF result to the client for display or print. In
        this way Inq maintains its minimal software requirements
        of the desktop environment to just a Java<sup>TM</sup>
        runtime environment and any suitable PDF reader associated with
        that file type.
      </p>
      <section id="rptcontent">
        <title>The XML Report Content</title>
        <p>
          The XSL templates used to transform the XML report content
          into Formatting Objects can be found
          at <code>reports/psreports.xsl</code>, which references the
          subordinate files <code>pagelayout.xsl</code>
          and <code>tableutils.xsl</code>. These templates
          have been written as examples and infer a particular layout
          of XML document they can process. You may have existing
          templates that require a different format of
          XML input document. In that case you will need
          to modify the Inq script that generates this file, so
          bear in mind that the explanation of petstore's
          reports includes a XML/XSL design that we do not dwell on
          here.
        </p>
        <p>
          Further discussion uses these examples of
          the <a href="reports/ordersummary.pdf">order summary</a>
          and <a href="reports/orderdetail.pdf">order detail</a> (pdf).
        </p>
        <p>
          The XML that generates these reports is respectively
          <a class="fork" href="reports/ordersummary.xml"><code>ordersummary.xml</code></a>
          and <a class="fork" href="reports/orderdetail.xml"><code>orderdetail.xml</code></a>.
          Here is a partially expanded view of <code>ordersummary.xml</code>:
        </p>
        <figure src="reports/ordersummary1.png" alt="ordersummary1"/>
        <p>
          The file contains four sections:
        </p>
        <dl>
          <dt><code>&lt;report&gt;</code></dt>
          <dd>
            Fixed information such as the report title and the footer.
          </dd>
          <dt><code>&lt;summarytable&gt;</code></dt>
          <dd>
            A tag to define the table caption, its columns and <em>where in the
            data section</em> the row data for this table should be extracted.
          </dd>
          <dt><code>&lt;data&gt;</code></dt>
          <dd>
            All the data for the report. For the Order Summary report this
            is the Account and the list of orders including the totals row.
          </dd>
          <dt><code>&lt;INQmetadata&gt;</code></dt>
          <dd>
            Meta-data about all the typedefs instances of which are present
            in the <code>&lt;data&gt;</code> section. Much like the Inq client
            GUI does, this information may
            be used by the templates to generate row headers, dimension columns
            and so forth.
          </dd>
        </dl>
        <p>
          The <code>&lt;data&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;INQmetadata&gt;</code>
          sections are known as <em>reference</em> sections
          whereas <code>&lt;report&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;summarytable&gt;</code>
          are called <em>content</em> sections.
        </p>
        <section id="templates">
          <title>How The Templates Work</title>
          <p>
            Briefly, the templates generate their Formatting Objects output by
            processing the <em>content</em> sections against
            the <code>&lt;data&gt;</code> section to provide the values
            and the <code>&lt;INQmetadata&gt;</code> section, where widths, labels
            and enumerations are held.
          </p>
          <p>
            Using attributes common to both, the templates use XPath expressions
            to extract information from the reference sections as directed by
            a particular element of the content.
          </p>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section id="ioxmlx">
        <title>The ioXMLX Stream</title>
        <p>
          Inq includes a <em>stream</em> type called <code>ioXMLX</code>
          which writes Inq structures to its sink as XML or parses XML from
          its source into an Inq structure.
        </p>
        <note>
          In Inq a particular stream type defines the format that data
          is read or written in (for example XML, plain text or some
          other format) and its connected source or sink the physical
          medium where it is read or written. Sources and sinks are
          specified with a URL syntax, such
          as <code>file://&lt;path&gt;</code>
          or <code>socket://&lt;host:port&gt;</code>
        </note>
        <p>
          Conversion of an Inq structure to XML involves the following steps:
        </p>
        <ol>
          <li>
            Declare a stream of type <code>ioXMLX</code>
          </li>
          <li>
            Configure the stream using the properties it supports
          </li>
          <li>
            Open the stream for writing, binding it to a sink 
          </li>
          <li>
            Write one (or more) values to the stream, closing it when done.
          </li>
        </ol>
        <p>
        </p>
        <section id="compare">
          <title>Comparing Inq and DOM Structures</title>
          <p>
            Before looking at this process in more detail, it is useful to
            compare Inq and <a class="fork" href="ext:DOM">Document Object
            Model</a> structures
            to see how they differ. An Inq structure is a simple containment
            hierarchy in which nodes are either maps, which may contain children,
            or leaves of some data type. In a map, the key set must be
            unique. Map children may or may not have an ordinal position. 
          </p>
          <p>
            In a DOM structure there are various node types
            including <em>elements</em>, <em>attributes</em>
            and <em>text</em>. Elements may contain other elements, attributes
            or text. Elements have a name and child elements do not have to
            be uniquely named in their parent. Text nodes are unnamed
            but their ordinal position, alongside that of their sibling
            elements, is significant.  
          </p>
          <p>
            The construction of a suitable Inq structure and use of an
            appropriately set up <code>ioXMLX</code> stream support the production
            of elements, attributes and text as either XML text, in-memory
            as a tree rooted at an instance of <code>org.w3c.dom.Document</code>
            or as <a class="fork" href="ext:JSON">JSON</a> text.
          </p>
        </section>
        <section id="ioxmlxconfig">
          <title>Configuring ioXMLX</title>
          <p>
            The <code>ioXMLX</code> stream supports the following properties
            used to configure its behaviour:
          </p>
          <table>
            <caption>ioXMLX Properties</caption>
            <tr>
              <th>Name</th>
              <th>Description</th>
              <th>Default</th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>cdata</td>
              <td>A <a href="../../primer/types.html#set"><code>set</code></a>
                of <a href="../../primer/nodes.html#pathfn"><code>path()</code></a>s
                that will be produced as <code>CDATA</code> sections. Otherwise
                numeric character references or character entity references
                are produced for markup and special characters.</td>
              <td></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>childName</td>
              <td>When writing node sets, the name given to the element
                  representing a node-set child.</td>
              <td><code>child</code></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>DOMOutput</td>
              <td>Generate output as an in-memory <code>org.w3c.dom.Document</code>.
                Must be set before the stream is opened</td>
              <td><code>false</code></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>enumExt</td>
              <td>When true produce any enumerated value fields as their external
                representation.</td>
              <td><code>false</code></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>excludesAt</td>
              <td>A <a href="../../primer/types.html#set"><code>set</code></a>
                of <a href="../../primer/nodes.html#pathfn"><code>path()</code></a>s
                that will be excluded (and therefore their children excluded)
                from the production.</td>
              <td></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>excludesBelow</td>
              <td>A <a href="../../primer/types.html#set"><code>set</code></a>
                of <a href="../../primer/nodes.html#pathfn"><code>path()</code></a>s
                that will themselves be produced but their children excluded
                from the production.</td>
              <td></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>formatOutput</td>
              <td>When producing XML or JSON text, whether the output will
                be formatted as indented lines for readability.</td>
              <td><code>true</code></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>formatters</td>
              <td>A map whose keys are <code>path()</code>s and values are
              formatters (or format patterns). When the traversal produces
              a scalar (generated as a <em>text</em> node) and the current
              path compares equals [TODO link] with a map key the corresponding
              format is applied.</td>
              <td></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>groupingUsed</td>
              <td>When <code>true</code> grouping separators are produced
                in numeric text; when <code>false</code> they are not. Of
                particular relevance to JSON output.</td>
              <td><code>true</code></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>includes</td>
              <td>As a complement to the <code>excludes[At,Below]</code>
                properties, a <code>set</code> of those paths that
                will be produced in the output; everything else
                will not be produced.</td>
              <td></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>inqAttributes</td>
              <td>When <a href="../../primer/structures.html#nodeset">node
                sets</a>, <code>typedef</code> instances and their fields
                are encountered, whether the production of these elements
                includes attributes that identify the element as such. See
                also <code>writeMeta</code> below.</td>
              <td></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>JSONOutput</td>
              <td>Generate output as JSON text.
                Must be set before the stream is opened</td>
              <td><code>false</code></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>metaFunc</td>
              <td>A function, which must be a <code>call()</code> statement,
                that will be called as the meta-data section of the output
                is produced. See following section. Can be used to manipulate
                the production of the meta-data, such as changing widths or
                labels from their typedef defaults. If set then also
                sets <code>writeMeta</code> to <code>true</code></td>
              <td></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>metaName</td>
              <td>The name of the root element for the meta-data section
                of the output. If set then also
                sets <code>writeMeta</code> to <code>true</code></td>
              <td><code>INQmetadata</code></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>preserveTypes</td>
              <td>When generating tags
                for <a href="../../primer/types.html#value-types">value types</a>
                whether type information is included in the output so
                that the same types are restored on input. If <code>false</code>
                then strings will be created.</td>
              <td><code>false</code></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>rootName</td>
              <td>The name of the root element of the produced document.</td>
              <td><code>root</code></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>seed</td>
              <td>A <code>map</code> used to seed the structure created when
                parsing XML.</td>
              <td><code>smap</code></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>tagFuncs</td>
              <td>A map whose keys are <code>path()</code>s and values are
              functions, which must be <code>call()</code> statements.
              As the traversal proceeds the path is maintained. If the current
              path compares equals [TODO link] with a map key the
              corresponding <em>tag function</em> is called. Used to manipulate
              the name of the element produced, apply attributes to it and
              manipulate any text content.</td>
              <td></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>tagNames</td>
              <td>A map whose keys are <code>path()</code>s and values are
              strings. If the current
              path compares equals with a map key the
              corresponding value is used as this element's name. Can be used
              instead of a <code>tagFunc</code> if the only requirement is
              a fixed element name change.</td>
              <td></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>writeMeta</td>
              <td>When <code>true</code> the meta-data section will be written
              to the output; when <code>false</code> it will not. If set
              to <code>true</code> then implies <code>inqAttributes</code>
              is also <code>true</code> and vice-versa.</td>
              <td><code>false</code></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>writeMultiple</td>
              <td>When <code>true</code> successive writes to the stream
              are enclosed in a <code>&lt;write&gt;</code> element;
              when <code>false</code> the stream is intended to produce
              its document with a single write operation on the root
              of the Inq structure.</td>
              <td><code>false</code></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>xmlPrologue</td>
              <td>When producing XML text (the default output format),
              the prologue to use. The default file encoding is included
              in the default value.</td>
              <td><code>&lt;?xml&nbsp;version="1.0" encoding="</code><em>default-platform-encoding</em><code>"?&gt;</code></td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>xmlOutput</td>
              <td>Generate output as XML text.</td>
              <td><code>true</code></td>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <p>
            By default, <code>ioXMLX</code> will generate an XML text document
            for a single Inq node structure, converting maps into elements
            containing child elements and leaves into elements with child text.
            By setting <code>writeMeta</code> to <code>true</code>
            the <code>&lt;INQmetadata&gt;</code> section is created automatically.
            Referring back to <code>ordersummary.xml</code>, for the other
            sections the remaining issues are
          </p>
          <ol>
            <li>
              generation of elements with repeated names, such
              as <code>&lt;column&gt;</code> - Inq does not allow duplicate
              names at a given level;
            </li>
            <li>
              production of any required attributes - Inq does not have
              any concept of different types of children, such as attributes
              and elements, as DOM does;
            </li>
            <li>
              the output is correctly ordered, for example
              the <code>&lt;column&gt;</code> elements must appear in
              order for the desired result in the PDF table and the
              rows (in the <code>&lt;data&gt;</code> section) appear by ascending
              order number, with the total row last.  
            </li>
          </ol>
          <p>
            These things can be achieved by building an appropriate Inq structure,
            sorted as necessary, and configuring <code>ioXMLX</code>.  
          </p>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section id="repsummary">
        <title>Focus on the Order Summary Report</title>
        <section id="inqstr">
          <title>Creating the Inq Structure</title>
          <p>
            Referring to <code>psReports.inq</code> the <code>ordersummary.xml</code>
            file is created by the function <code>createSummaryXML()</code>. It is
            passed the current filter from the GUI which it uses to re-fetch
            the current order set, in this case using an ordered
            map (an <code>omap</code>) to seed the structure: 
          </p>
          <source>
local function createSummaryXML(any filter)
{
  omap m;
  any root.data.orders  = call filterOrders(filter, root = m);
</source>
          <p>
            Notice that the node <code>root.data.orders</code> has been created - the
            node <code>data</code> is the beginnings of what will become
            the <code>&lt;data&gt;</code> tag in the XML production. Next, the
            total row for the report is created by making a new instance
            of <code>Order</code>, setting its <code>TotalPrice</code> field
            to the sum of the orders and placing it in the structure alongside them:
          </p>
          <source>
  any total = new(Order);
  total.TotalPrice = sum(root.data.orders, $loop.Order.TotalPrice);
  any root.data.orders.total.Order = total;
</source>
          <p>
            The <code>orders</code> node is
            an <a href="../../primer/types.html#omap"><code>omap</code></a>, so it
            supports vector access and therefore sorting. The table rows
            appear in ascending order of date and order number, according to
            the outcome of this use of <code>sort</code>: 
          </p>
          <source>
  sort(root.data.orders, $loop.Order.OrderDate, $loop.Order.Order, null=NULL_HIGH);
</source>
          <p>
            The Order at <code>root.data.orders.total.Order</code> has uninitialised
            fields <code>Order.Order</code> and <code>Order.OrderDate</code>. These
            fields have no default value set for them in the typedef, so they
            have the value <code>null</code>. By telling <code>sort()</code>
            that <code>null</code> sorts above non-null values with the optional
            argument <code>null=NULL_HIGH</code> the total row will be at the end
            of the vector.
          </p>
          <p>
            The user's Account is required for the report, so this is added
            to the <code>&lt;data&gt;</code> section. The <code>&lt;report&gt;</code>
            tag contains the title and disclaimer:
          </p>
          <source>
  any root.data.Account        = call getAccount();
  any root.report.title        = "Order Summary"; // TODO i18n
  any root.report.disclaimer   = call disclaimer();
</source>
          <p>
            The Inq function <code>renderf</code> formats a string as
            for <a class="fork" href="ext:j2seapi/apidocs/messageformat">MessageFormat</a>
            with the additional semantics that if typedef fields are referenced
            their format pattern is used. To make use of this petstore defines
            the typedef <code>ReportHelper</code> (see <code>ReportHelper.inq</code>).
            To create the table caption an instance of ReportHelper is
            initialised from the filter's From and To dates. The rendered text
            is then placed in the omap <code>root.summarytable</code>:
          </p>
          <source>
  any helper = new(ReportHelper, filter);

  omap root.summarytable;
  
  any root.summarytable.caption = renderf("Your orders between {0} and {1}:",
                                          helper.FromDate,
                                          isnull(helper.ToDate, "Today"));
</source>
          <p>
            An omap is used so that as columns are added their order
            is preserved. According to the requirements of an Inq map's
            unique key set, the columns are set up like this:
          </p>
          <source>
  any root.summarytable.OrderNumber = null;
  any root.summarytable.OrderDate   = null;
  any root.summarytable.OrderTotal  = null;
</source>
          <p>
            The values are not important, in fact the column tags in the
            XML are empty. The
            names, <code>OrderNumber</code>, <code>OrderDate</code>
            and <code>OrderTotal</code> are picked up by a <em>tag function</em>
            so that a <code>&lt;column&gt;</code> tag with the required
            attributes can be produced. Furthermore, data for the table
            rows must be retrieved from somewhere so we need to generate
            the <code>&lt;from&gt;</code> tag:
          </p>
          <source>
  any root.summarytable.from        = null;
</source>
        </section>
        <section id="useioxmlx">
          <title>Using ioXMLX</title>
          <p>
            Having built an Inq structure that looks <em>somewhat</em> like
            the XML document we want we are ready to apply it
            to <code>ioXMLX</code>. The stream is declared and
            the <code>tagFuncs</code> property set so script can intervene
            during the traversal to manipulate the output:
          </p>
          <source>
  // Now write the xml out. Declare a stream
  ioXMLX strm;

  object p = path($this.summarytable.%);
  any tagFuncs.{p} = cfunc f = call orderSummaryChild(nodeset = getnodeset(root.data.orders));
  strm.properties.tagFuncs = tagFuncs;
</source>
          <p>
            As stated above, this property is a map of <code>path</code>s to
            call statement functions. In order to get a <code>path</code> to
            be a map key it must be protected from expansion as
            an <a href="../../primer/nodes.html#elementsub">indirect path</a>
            by placing it inside an <code>object</code> variable.
          </p>
          <note>
            In general, variables of type <code>object</code> allow foreign
            objects (like a DOM tree for example) to be carried around in the
            Inq environment.
          </note>
          <p>
            When is the tag function called and what does it do?
            As <code>ioXMLX</code> traverses an Inq structure it maintains the
            path of the current node. If this path matches a key in the
            current <code>tagFuncs</code> then that function is called
            before the corresponding element is produced.
            Here is the signature of <code>orderSummaryChild()</code>:
          </p>
          <source>
local function orderSummaryChild(any nodeset,   // &lt;- argument(s) from script
                                 any node,      // &lt;- arguments Inq supplies
                                 any parent,    // v
                                 any nodeName,
                                 any ordinal,
                                 any content,
                                 any last,
                                 any descend,
                                 any attributes)
</source>
          <p>
            The <code>nodeset</code> argument is explicitly provided in the call
            to the function. The other arguments are provided by <code>ioXMLX</code>
            and have these meanings:
          </p>
          <table>
            <caption>Tag Function Arguments</caption>
            <tr>
              <th>Name</th>
              <th>Description</th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>node</td>
              <td>The current Inq node</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>parent</td>
              <td>The parent of the current Inq node</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>nodeName</td>
              <td>The name of the current node (that is its key in its parent)</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>ordinal</td>
              <td>The zero-based ordinal position of this node in its parent. If
                the parent does not support vector access then this argument is
                still supplied but does not infer order. It should be considered
                as a simple counter.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>content</td>
              <td>If custom content is to be produced the tag function may
                return it by setting the value of this argument.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>last</td>
              <td><code>true</code> if this is the last child of the current
                parent, <code>false</code> if it is not.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>descend</td>
              <td>Initialised to <code>true</code> before the function
                is called, may be set to <code>false</code> to prevent
                the current node being descended into.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>attributes</td>
              <td>A map that the function may populate
                with <code>string</code> key/value pairs that will
                be produced as XML attributes on the produced element.</td>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <p>
            The return value of a tag function is the desired element name.
            If this is <code>nodeName</code> then that argument should be
            returned. If <code>null</code> is returned then the current
            element is not produced in the output (and not descended into).
          </p>
          <p>
            Here is the body of <code>orderSummaryChild()</code>:
          </p>
          <source>
  any ret = "column";
  
  switch
  {
    when(nodeName == "from")
    {
      any attributes.nodeset = nodeset;
      
      // Leave the tag name as it is
      any ret = nodeName;
    }

    when(nodeName == "caption")
    {
      // Leave the tag name as it is
      any ret = nodeName;
    }
    
    when(nodeName == "OrderNumber")
    {
      any attributes.typedef = fqname(typedef(Order));
      any attributes.field   = "Order";
      any attributes.halign  = "center";  // used by table cell generation
    }

    when(nodeName == "OrderDate")
    {
      any attributes.typedef = fqname(typedef(Order));
      any attributes.field   = "OrderDate";
    }

    when(nodeName == "OrderTotal")
    {
      any attributes.typedef = fqname(typedef(Order));
      any attributes.field   = "TotalPrice";
    }
    
    // Don't produce a tag for anything we were not expecting
    otherwise
      any ret = null;

  }
  
  ret;
</source>
          <p>
            and referring to the sample XML output <a href="#rptcontent">above</a>
            we can see how this script plays its part in transforming the
            original Inq node structure into the desired result.
          </p>
          <p class="vignette">
            As noted above, the chosen XML production relates to the
            processing by xlst templates into Formatting Objects. Out of
            interest, how does this work? Considering the orders table
            defined by <code>&lt;summarytable&gt;</code>,
            the templates find the root of the rows data by tieing together
            the <code>@nodeset</code> attribute of the <code>&lt;from&gt;</code>
            tag with the element underneath <code>&lt;data&gt;</code>
            whose <code>@nodeset</code> attribute has the same value.
          </p>
          <figure class="vignette" src="reports/ordersummary2.png" alt="ordersummary2"/>
          <p class="vignette">
            Similarly for the column data, the <code>@typedef</code>
            and <code>@field</code> attributes are matched up as shown.
          </p>
          <p>
            The total row has a currency symbol in its formatted result. To
            achieve this we can override the default
            formatting (specified in its typedef) of
            the <code>Order.TotalPrice</code> field.
            The <code>formatters</code> property is set up in the same way
            as <code>tagFuncs</code> was, mapping the path whose format
            is to be established to a format pattern:
          </p>
          <source>
  object p = path($this*total.Order.TotalPrice);
  any formatters.{p} = "#,##0.00";
  strm.properties.formatters = formatters;

  call writeXMLFile(strm, root, rootElementName = "ordersummary");
</source>
          <p>
            Having set up those properties specific to the order summary
            report, the remaining work to generate the XML file
            is carried out in the helper
            function  <code>writeXMLFile()</code>
          </p>
          <source>
local function writeXMLFile(any strm,
                            any root,
                            any rootElementName)
{
  any repXml = createtmpfile($process.loginName, ".xml");
  try
  {
    strm.properties.rootName = rootElementName;

    strm.properties.metaFunc = cfunc f = call metaTags(priceCurrency = $catalog.{$root.i18n}.ps.CURRENCY);
    
    open(strm, repXml, OPEN_WRITE);
    writestream(strm, root);
  }
  finally
  {
    close(strm);
    
    // returns
    // Note: the Inq "file" type yields a URL syntax when converted to a string.
    // We want the file system's path instead. 
    repXml.properties.canonicalPath;
  }
}
</source>
          <p>
            In this function the stream's <code>metaFunc</code> property is set.
            Setting this property implies also that
            the <code>&lt;INQmetadata&gt;</code>
            section will be produced. Here is a sample from the order summary
            production:
          </p>
          <figure src="reports/ordersummary3.png" alt="ordersummary3"/>
          <p>
            As <code>ioXMLX</code> encounters typedef instances during the traversal
            so it writes out their metadata as shown. Within
            each <code>&lt;INQfield&gt;</code> tag at most the following can
            appear:
          </p>
          <table>
            <tr>
              <th>Tag</th>
              <th>Description</th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <code>&lt;INQisnumeric&gt;</code>
              </td>
              <td>
                Present if the field is a numeric value and has the
                text content <code>true</code>. Absent otherwise
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <code>&lt;INQwidth&gt;</code>
              </td>
              <td>
                The width of the field
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <code>&lt;INQlabel&gt;</code>
              </td>
              <td>
                The label of the field
              </td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>
                <code>&lt;INQenum&gt;</code>
              </td>
              <td>
                Any enumerations the field has. The internal value is
                given by the attribute <code>@INQinternal</code> and
                the external value is the content. Repeated for each
                enumerated value of the field.
              </td>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <p>
            The <code>&lt;INQtypedef&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;INQfield&gt;</code>
            tags respectively have the <code>@INQfqname</code>
            and <code>@INQname</code> attributes that allow templates to
            make use of the metadata. The sample templates do this to
            generate the table headers, dimension the columns and
            right-justify numeric values.
          </p>
          <p>
            A <code>metaFunc</code> is called once for each field within
            each typedef and allows script to control what gets
            produced in the <code>&lt;INQmetadata&gt;</code> section, so that
            if the typedef defaults are not suitable alternatives can be
            provided. Here is what our example does: 
          </p>
          <source>
local function metaTags(any priceCurrency,  // &lt;- argument(s) from script
                        any Typedef,         // &lt;- arguments Inq supplies
                        any Field,           // v
                        any Label,
                        any Width)
{
  switch
  {
    when (Typedef == typedef(Order) &amp;&amp; Field == "ShipCity")
    {
      Label = "Shipping\nCity";
    }
    
    when (Typedef == typedef(LineItem) &amp;&amp; Field == "UnitPrice")
    {
      Label = "Unit Price\n" + priceCurrency.properties.symbol;
    }
    
    when(Typedef == typedef(ValueHelper) &amp;&amp; Field == "Price")
    {
      Label = "Total Price\n" + priceCurrency.properties.symbol;
    }
  }
}
</source>
          <p>
            The <code>priceCurrency</code> argument is explicitly provided in the call
            to the function. The other arguments are provided by <code>ioXMLX</code>
            and have these meanings:
          </p>
          <table>
            <caption>Tag Function Arguments</caption>
            <tr>
              <th>Name</th>
              <th>Description</th>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Typedef</td>
              <td>The typedef whose metadata is being produced</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Field</td>
              <td>The field whose metadata is being produced</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Label</td>
              <td>The default label. The function can assign an alternative
                value to this argument.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td>Width</td>
              <td>The default width. The function can assign an alternative
                value to this argument.</td>
            </tr>
          </table>
          <p>
            We can see that some columns have a new-line in them. It is
            also possible to access a currency symbol (via property access and
            Inq's <code>currency</code> data type) and include this in the
            header. [Note: <a href="reports/orderdetail.pdf">orderdetail.pdf</a>
            uses these].
          </p>
          <p>
            Lastly, the stream is opened to a temporary file and the XML
            created with the call of <code>writestream(strm, root);</code>.
          </p>
        </section>
        <section id="genpdf">
          <title>Generating the PDF Output</title>
          <p>
            Having discussed <code>createSummaryXML()</code>, the order summary pdf
            is created by the following function:
          </p>
          <source>
local function orderSummary(any filter, any ack)
{
  // Create the xml report file.
  any xml = call createSummaryXML(filter);
  
  // Generate the pdf report
  any pdf = call generatePdf(xml); 

  // Return the generated file name to client. It then performs
  // a file transfer request  
  send updateOk(item = pdf, ack);
}
</source>
          <p>
            The local variable <code>xml</code> is the path of the file in which
            the XML production of the report has been created. What
            does <code>generatePdf()</code> do with this? Here is
            what that function looks like:
          </p>
          <source>
local function generatePdf(any xml)
{
  // xsl scripted report transform
  any xsl = call makeXslFile();
  
  // Where the result will end up
  any pdf = call makeOutputFile();
                      
  any c = "fop -xml {0} -xsl {1} -pdf {2}";
  string cmd = renderf(c, xml, xsl, pdf);

  // Put stderr in a string stream and if fop's exit status is not
  // zero throw the string content.
  string err;
  ioPrint perr;
  open(perr, "string://err", OPEN_WRITE);
  
  // syscmd closes any streams it is given so we don't have to
  if (syscmd(cmd, stdout=$catalog.system.out, stderr=perr) &amp;&amp; err)
    throw(cmd + err);

  // Returns
  call inq.filexfer:makeRelativeToRoot(filename = pdf);
}
</source>
          <p>
            In fact, this is more a demonstration of Inq interfacing with
            the command line on the host. The important points are these:
          </p>
          <ol>
            <li>
              Build the command line to
              run <a class="fork" href="ext:fop">Apache FOP</a> using
              the <code>renderf</code> function described above. 
            </li>
            <li>
              Create a <code>ioPrint</code> stream and open it to write
              to a <code>string</code> variable.
            </li>
            <li>
              Run the command using Inq's <code>syscmd</code> function, capturing
              anything it writes to <code>stderr</code> and throwing an exception
              should there be any and <code>fop</code> has a non-zero exit status.
            </li>
          </ol>
          <p>
            For completeness and the sake of showing additional Inq features in use,
            here are the subordinate functions <code>generatePdf()</code> calls:
          </p>
          <source>
local function makeXslFile()
{
  // Expecting to find a directory ./reports relative to this inq source
  // file, where the reports are scripted as xslt.
  file xsl = absurl("reports" +
                    $properties.file_separator +
                    "psreports.xsl");
                      
  xsl.properties.canonicalPath;
}
</source>
          <ol>
            <li>
              The <code>absurl()</code> function converts a relative
              path into an absolute URL string using either a specified
              absolute URL as the base as its second argument or (as here) the
              URL of the executing script is assumed. 
            </li>
            <li>
              A variable of type <code>file</code> is assigned from
              the absolute URL. This is just so that a path of the
              form <code>/some/absolute/path/psreports.xsl</code>
              can be retrieved using the file's <code>canonicalPath</code>
              property. The <code>fop</code> command requires file paths,
              not <code>file:</code> URLs.
            </li>
          </ol>
          <source>
local function makeOutputFile()
{
  // The three-argument version of createtmpfile takes prefix, suffix
  // and directory. We are expecting to find &lt;filexfer&gt;/tmp as the
  // output directory.
  any f = createtmpfile($process.loginName,
                        ".pdf",
                        call inq.filexfer:makeAbsoluteFromRoot(filename = "tmp"));

  f.properties.canonicalPath;
}
</source>
          <ol>
            <li>
              The <code>createtmpfile()</code> function returns a variable
              of type <code>file</code>, generating a name from the prefix,
              an optional suffix and in an optional directory. If no directory
              is specified the host's default temporary directory is used. 
            </li>
            <li>
              The Inq bundled <code>inq.filexfer</code> package is discussed
              elsewhere [TODO]
            </li>
          </ol>
          <p>
            The Order Detail report uses the same techniques and helper
            functions as Order Summary. There is only one thing it does
            differently, just for the sake of pointing it out.
            In <code>createDetailXML()</code> the formatter for the Total Price
            cell of the order (not the items) table is created like this:
          </p>
          <source>
object p3 = path($this.data.Order.TotalPrice);
any priceFormatter = format("#,##0.00", Order.TotalPrice);
any formatters.{p3} = priceFormatter;
strm.properties.formatters = formatters;
</source>
          <p>
            The <code>format()</code> function creates a <em>formatter</em>, in
            this case saving <code>ioXMLX</code> the trouble of doing so. It
            requires a variable whose type (numeric or date) is suitable for
            the pattern specified. Property support in formatters allows things
            like grouping separators to be disabled, negative prefix and suffix
            access and more [TODO].
          </p>
        </section>
      </section>
      <p>
        <a href="items.html"><icon src="../images/nextpage.gif" alt="nextpage"/></a>
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
